Muhammad Hamza Sharif

Google Scholar: scholar.google.com

Mobile: +971-50-533-0642

Github: github.com/Sharifmhamza

Email: sharifmhamza@gmail.com

PERSONAL STATEMENT

My research interests focus on computer vision applications particularly in biomedical imaging and remote sensing domain. I am interested in developing and applying deep learning methods for segmentation, detection, and reconstruction tasks and also interested to learn and use the knowledge of multi-modal data to understand these domain in a better way.

EDUCATION

Mohamed bin Zayed University of Artificial Intelligence (MBZUAI), Abudhabi UAE

Masters in Science in Computer Vision

Aug. 2021 - June 2023

o CGPA: 3.91 on scale of 4.00

• Thesis: "Exploring the potential of deep learning approaches for Biomedical Image Segmentation" Link

o Advisors: Primary : Dr. Min Xu, Secondary : Dr. Muhammad Yaqub

University of Engineering and Technology (UET), Lahore Pakistan

Bachelor of Science in Computer Engineering

Sept. 2013 - Aug. 2017

o CGPA: 3.521 on scale of 4.00

o Thesis: "iFruitfly Detector: An Intelligent System for food Quality Control" Link

o Advisor: Dr. Sheikh Faisal Rashid

SKILLS

Development Languages, Tools & Frameworks: Python, R, SQL, Anaconda, Visual Studio, Git, Linux, Tableau ML & DL Libraries and Frameworks: pandas, numpy, scipy, statsmodel, scikit-learn, keras, pytorch, plotly Computer Vision & NLP Libraries: Opency, detectron2, MONAI, nibabel, SimpleITK, NLTK Databases: MySQL/Maria DB, SQL Server, Talend, Google Big Query

EXPERIENCE

Data Analyst - AI

Afiniti Karachi, Pakistan Link

Feb. 2021 - Aug. 2021

- Responsible for developing maintaining, and optimizing data pipelines for various international clients.
- o Developing and deploying ETL routines and write complex SQL procedures for various data intensive workflows.

Machine Learning Engineer

Ephlux Karachi, Pakistan Link

Dec. 2019 - Aug. 2020

- Responsible for collecting and processing data from different sources, performing data profiling, preliminary data analysis, and interpreting results using statistical techniques.
- Responsible for model development, model validation, model deployment, and model explainability for medical datasets using the SHAP library.
- \circ Implement NLP based model for semantic text similarity problems for the medical corpus.

Research Associate

Barrett Hodgson University (BHU) Karachi, Pakistan Link

May 2018 - Nov. 2019

- o Conduct research in the computational neuroscience domain for automatic detection of autism using MRI scans.
- Responsible for implementing deep learning methods by scientific studies in a multidisciplinary domain.

DAAD Research Intern

Deutsches Forschungszentrum für Künstliche Intelligenz (DFKI) Germany Link

July 2016 - Sept. 2016

• I have worked on fruit fly identification problem in fruits using thermography and machine learning techniques. For that purpose, I have implemented image processing algorithms and build ML classifiers using python. I also learned how to use rapidminer and weka tools during my internship.

Research & Projects

- Object Detection in Aerial: Imagery Improving the Performance of Faster R-CNN on iSAID Dataset In this project we used different techniques to enhance the efficiency of the Faster R-CNN detector when applied to aerial imagery. Through the implementation of various strategies, we were able to improve the average precision to 42.7%, resulting in a 5.5% improvement as compare to the original model.) Link.
- Improving Latent Space of Generative Adversarial Networks (GANs) In this project, I have proposed new method that combine a self-supervised contrastive learning approach with generative adversarial learning to generate images with greater control over their underlying representations.
- Patient Experience PX-PULSE I have developed an API for the patient length of stay in hospital-based upon patient disease and condition using a regression technique. Getting the data using API request, pre-processing and transforming the dataset by imputing the missing values, dumping dataset into Flask-SQLAlchemy database, and applying regression technique.
- Ante Natal Risk Identification using Fetal Doppler This is a collaborative research-based project between Ephlux, AKUH, and Boston Children Hospital. I have developed a model using XGBoost for antenatal risk identification using fetal doppler through hyper-parameter tuning of the model using Grid-Search and interpreting the model using Shapely Values.
- iFruitFly Detector: An intelligent System for food Quality Control This is a collaborative research project funded by DAAD for the automatic identification of mangoes infested with fruit flies. Hand crafted pixel-based features are calculated using frames of thermal video of mangoes. A two-layer MLP identifies healthy and non-healthy mango with an accuracy of 94.18%. Using the DB-SCAN clustering algorithm, regions in the infested mangoes are marked. MLP also identifies infested regions with an accuracy of 94.00%.

PUBLICATIONS

- Dmitry Demidov, Muhammad Hamza Sharif, Aliakbar Abdurahimov, Hisham Cholakkal, Fahad Khan. Salient Mask-Guided Vision Transformer for Fine-Grained Classification. (VISAPP-2023-Oral Best Paper Award) Link
- Muhammad Hamza Sharif, Dmitry Demidov, Asif Hanif, Mohammad Yaqub, Min Xu. TransResNet: Integrating the Strengths of ViTs and CNNs for High Resolution Medical Image Segmentation via Feature Grafting. (BMVC-2022) Link
- Muneera A. Rasheed, Prem Chand, Saad Ahmed, Hamza Sharif, Zahra Hoodbhoy, Ayat Siddiqui, Babar S. Hasan. Use of
 artificial intelligence on Electroencephalogram (EEG) waveforms to predict failure in early school grades in children from a
 rural cohort in Pakistan Link
- Hamza Sharif, Rizwan Ahmed Khan. A novel framework for automatic detection of autism: A study on corpus callosum and intracranial brain volume Link

AWARDS & ACCOLADES

• Awarded fully funded Masters Scholarship at MBZUAI

• Awarded for winning 3rd place **Hack for Space Hackathon** powered by G42 (1000dhs)

• Research Internship Award (1000 Euro/month Summer @DAAD Award)

References

Name: Dr. Min Xu

Designation: Associate Professor, Computational Biology Department at CMU Affiliated Associate Professor, Computer Vision Department at MBZUAI

Email: xumin100@gmail.com

Name: Dr. Mohammad Yaqub

Designation: Associate Professor, Computer Vision Department at MBZUAI

Email: mohammad.yaqub@mbzuai.ac.ae

Name: Dr. Kun Zhang

Designation: Associate professor, Philosophy Department at CMU Associate Professor, Machine Learning Department at MBZUAI

Email: kun.zhang@mbzuai.ac.ae